<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bryn Hughes</title>
    <description>Musician, professor, nerd. Lover of hockey and pugs.</description>
    <link>//</link>
    <atom:link href="//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>In Defense of Music Theory</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, one of my graduate students emailed me a link to an
article published on Slate.com. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slate.com/blogs/quora/2014/02/17/teaching_music_theory_how_can_modern_music_mix_with_traditional_theory.html&quot;&gt;“How Can Traditional Music Theory Mesh
With Modern Pop
Music?”&lt;/a&gt;
purports that music theory, as it’s taught in university music programs
across North America, “serves practicing musicians pretty poorly.” The
author, NYU graduate student Ethan Hein, proposes that music theory
pedagogy should recast its mission and objectives to better suit the
needs of today’s musicians, who are more interested in popular music
than repertoire drawn from the common practice. Though he never really
defines what he means by this, we can assume he’s referring to the
typical “Bach to Brahms” canon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article resonated with me. I seem to frequently respond to people
who suggest that what we learn in music theory class is “irrelevant and
useless, since we’re not eighteenth-century court musicians.” Fine,
nobody has ever really said exactly that to me. If they did, I think I
would fall out of my chair. But many students over the years have asked
me to explain to them how music theory is “relevant to their musical
lives.” The tone of Hein’s article reminded me of these students.
Perhaps more importantly, the article was being “published” (curated?)
by Slate, a seemingly reputable journalistic website, and Hein was being
touted as some kind of “music theory expert.” Moreover, Hein’s blog had
gained significant traction on Reddit and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.slate.com%2Fblogs%2Fquora%2F2014%2F02%2F17%2Fteaching_music_theory_how_can_modern_music_mix_with_traditional_theory.html&amp;amp;src=typd&amp;amp;f=realtime&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;,
having been promoted by popular writers &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dylanmatt/status/438725519455305728&quot;&gt;such as Dylan
Matthews&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ThatEricAlper/status/437663314093830144&quot;&gt;Eric
Alper&lt;/a&gt;. My
dear beloved field of music theory was being smeared all over the
internet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I disagreed with several of the claims he made in his post, and as we do
in today’s society, I took to Twitter to air my grievances. Through the
magic of the internet, I was soon thrust into a conversation with Hein
about his article. While I love Twitter, it isn’t a great venue for
lengthy debate. I promised Hein (who turns out to be a really nice guy)
that I would write a “counterpoint” to his article, in which I more
clearly spelled out exactly how I thought he was misrepresenting the
discipline of music theory. And here we are. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hein begins his discussion by describing what he sees as one of the
central problems with music education today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The academic music world is slowly coming to grips with the ways
that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ethanhein.com/wp/2013/against-music-theory/&quot;&gt;conventional teaching of music
theory&lt;/a&gt; serves
practicing musicians pretty poorly.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first of several straw-man arguments (which I learned
recently is called an &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Straw_man&quot;&gt;“Aunt
Sally”&lt;/a&gt; in the United Kingdom!)
posed throughout the article. What evidence is there that music
theorists are “coming to grips” with the failings of their own teaching?
I certainly haven’t seen any “crisis of faith” panels at any recent
meetings of the Society for Music Theory. Moreover, by what measurement
can we determine the degree to which music theory classes have
benefitted musicians? Most of what is taught in undergraduate theory
curricula is rudimentary, and becomes deeply ingrained into our
students’ musical knowledge. Students who have gone through our classes
may not be able to articulate exactly what it is that they gained from
studying counterpoint, but that doesn’t mean that studying counterpoint
hasn’t had a positive impact on their musicianship or their careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hein’s main premise is that today’s music students draw upon a diversity
of musical experience, especially popular music. He suggests that, while
some scholars have become proponents of studying popular music in the
academy, music theorists have primarily ignored this repertoire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The pop music pedagogy movement, spearheaded by &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucy_Green&quot;&gt;Lucy
Green&lt;/a&gt;, is doing some
creative work aimed at aligning music education with the way people
experience and understand music in the present.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, Lucy Green and several other scholars have done some tremendous
research into the use of popular music in the public school system.
However, I don’t think that many music theorists, or even Green herself,
would really consider her work to be “music theory,” and it’s not really
appropriate to compare her work to what might be seen as lacking in
music theory scholarship or the classroom. Moreover, it’s a bit
ridiculous to suggest that what is successful in general music programs
in public schools can be automatically be transferred to conservatories
and universities that train would-be professional musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hein then gets into dangerous territory in attempting to define music
theory and its purpose. This is a question that I pose to my graduate
students every year, and it’s definitely a tough nut to crack:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We should be asking: What is it that musicians are doing that
sounds good? What patterns can we detect in the broad mass of music
being made and enjoyed out there in the world?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, music theory does not attempt to discern what sounds
good or bad. Music theory certainly helps explain why a chord might
sound dissonant in one context and not another, but questions such as
whether a piece sounds “good” or “bad,” or why a piece is popular, are
much more difficult to answer. Learning music theory, more than
anything, is about “learning to think in music.” It’s about developing
the critical thinking skills and musicianship necessary to engage more
deeply with musical performance, composition, and interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hein tries further to suggest that music theory needs to ground itself
in a “common practice,” and that most music programs are grounding it in
the wrong “common practice”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I have my own set of ideas about what constitutes common-practice
music in America in 2014, but I also come with my set of biases and
preferences. It would be better to have some hard data on what we all
collectively think makes for valid music.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I don’t think the purpose of a music theory class (or any music
class, really), is to solely concentrate on a “common practice”, nor
even to try to discern what a common practice might be. More egregious,
though, is that Hein asserts that (his) music theory professors equate
common practice with musical validity. He goes on to cite a wonderful
study by Trevor de Clercq and David Temperley that investigates harmonic
usage in rock music (loosely defined by the Rolling Stone Top 500 list)
as a means of “proving” that music no longer works in the way that his
stodgy, ivory-tower dwelling theory professors would have you believe.
Let’s unpack all of the things that are wrong with this sentiment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though the Temperley and de Clercq study indeed reveals some
differences in harmonic usage between common practice and rock music,
Hein fails to mention the tremendous amount of overlap that exists
between these two styles (my own dissertation investigates this idea as
well). The music of Bach is certainly markedly different from that of
Jimi Hendrix, but discussing them using a common language isn’t akin to
comparing apples to beavers. We can safely talk about the commonalities
and celebrate the differences. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Music theory professors are not concerned with finding “musical
validity.” Literally nobody I’ve ever met in my nearly 15 years working
in the environment of university music programs has tried to tell me
that they’ve found the “ultimate musical truth.” A music theory graduate
student who proposed that they did find something like this would be
laughed out of the program.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Though I can’t speak for every music theory teacher in the Western
world (though it should be noted that neither can Hein, even though he
tries to), I can say that in my classes, I strive more than anything to
empower my students with the ability to speak intelligently about the
technical musical differences between disparate styles. I want them to
be able to talk about how and why rock music’s harmony is used
differently than the harmony found in the music of Bach or Beethoven (or
even why Bach’s use of harmony is different from Beethoven’s). In order
to do so, my students need to understand voice leading and harmonic
syntax, and how that differs in the music of Bach, Beethoven, Mahler,
Schoenberg, The Beatles, Thelonious Monk, Stevie Wonder, and The Wu-Tang
Clan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I certainly haven’t conducted a thorough study of all of the
theory curricula across the country, I can still point to the growing
body of scholarship produced by people like Walter Everett, John Covach,
Allan Moore, Nicole Biamonte, David Temperley, Mark Butler, Tim Hughes,
Anna Stephan-Robinson, Guy Capuzzo, Jocelyn Neal, Fred Maus, Adam Krims,
Mark Spicer, Joti Rockwell, Jay Summach, Drew Nobile, Brad Osborn, Kyle
Adams, Chris Endrinal, Victoria Malawey, Dave Easley, Christopher Doll,
Greg McCandless, and countless others over the last 20 years to show
that popular music has a prominent place within the world of music
theory. Moreover, this scholarship has trickled down into nearly every
major music theory textbook that has been published in recent history.
Heck, at their 2011 meeting, the Society for Music Theory staged a
formal public debate, attended by hundreds of theory professors, that
directly addressed the very issues that Hein claims we don’t ever think
about. The resolution of the “Great Theory Debate” was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Be It Resolved … Common-Practice Period Repertoire No Longer Speaks to
Our Students; It’s Time to Fire A Cannon at the Canon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To suggest that music theory as a discipline is purely invested in the
music of the common practice from Bach to Brahms is simply wrong. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of what Hein writes in his Slate article is drawn from earlier
posts on his blog. In &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ethanhein.com/wp/2013/against-music-theory/&quot;&gt;“Against Music
Theory,”&lt;/a&gt; Hein
explains why he felt so compelled to investigate a “new music theory”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I am mercifully finished with music theory in grad school and
couldn’t be happier about it. You may find this surprising. My blog is
full of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ethanhein.com/wp/category/music/music-theory/&quot;&gt;music
theory&lt;/a&gt;. How
could a guy who enjoys thinking about music in analytical terms as
much as I do have such a wretched time in my graduate music theory
classes? It wasn’t the work, I mostly breezed through that. No, it was
the grinding
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurocentrism&quot;&gt;Eurocentrism&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_practice_period&quot;&gt;Common-practice
period&lt;/a&gt; classical
music theory is fine and good, but in the hands of the music academy,
it’s dry, tedious, and worst of all, largely useless. The strict rules
of eighteenth-century European art music are distantly removed from
the knowledge a person needs to do anything in the present-day music
world (except, I guess, to be a professor of common-practice tonal
theory.)”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terrible music theory teachers who don’t provide their students with a
broader context in their classes surely exist. But terrible teachers of
calculus, medieval history, economics, and marine biology also exist.
That these classes are a waste of time is a failure of the teacher, not
the discipline. At the heart of this is an argument that I hear a lot
from younger students: “I don’t see the immediate utility of what we’re
learning and how it relates to my current interests, so it is obviously
useless to me.” I think this attitude is dangerous, especially among
those who are dedicated to higher education. Ultimately, university is
not meant to be job training. We go to university to become
intellectually-engaged critical thinkers; to become better members of
society. While I’ve just spent several hundred words explaining why I
think music theory is a diverse discipline that is relevant to today’s
musicians, I don’t think that investing time in learning something that
might seem esoteric is a worthless endeavour. As students of music we
should yearn to become musical experts; strive to become knowledgeable
about all of its facets, from Josquin to Cecil Taylor to A$AP Rocky. If
we have to constantly justify the immediate value of what we study, we
will eventually fall into the same rhetorical trap that politicians use
to question the value of studying music at all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//2014/02/27/in-defense-of-music-theory/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//2014/02/27/in-defense-of-music-theory/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Maple Leafs Forever. Unfortunately.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One great thing about living in Miami is the presence of the Florida
Panthers. Don’t get me wrong–it’s patently absurd that there is a
professional hockey team in South Florida. But as a transplanted,
die-hard hockey fan, I have grown to appreciate that the Panthers’
desperate attempts to draw fans to their games means that I get to see
my beloved Maple Leafs for a fraction of the cost of a ticket at the ACC
in Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, my friend Nick and I sat in the second row, just inside the
blue line, to see the Leafs take on the Panthers. We were surrounded by
Leafs fans who had flown to South Florida to see the Leafs, because it
was cheaper to fly to Fort Lauderdale (the Panthers play in nearby
Sunrise), pay for a hotel and a lower-bowl ticket, than it was to see
the Leafs at home. Plus they got to enjoy 80 degrees in the sunshine in
February. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the Leafs were significantly outplayed by the lowly
Panthers. If you know anything about the Leafs, you’d know that they’re
one of professional sports’ most frustrating franchises. They’re
surrounded by endless media hype, and have been disappointing their fans
year after year since their last Stanley Cup win in 1967. The Maple
Leafs are the Chicago Cubs of the NHL. The Leafs are Fredo Corleone:
weak and stupid. The Leafs are the drunk and embarrassing uncle at
Thanksgiving dinner; a travesty, but you have to love them anyway,
because they’re family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Leafs came to Florida riding a six-game winning streak. The Panthers
are a consistently and comically awful team. My friend Nick suggested a
friendly wager:  if the Leafs won, he would pay for the tickets. If the
Panthers won, I would pay for the tickets. Perhaps I was just awestruck
by our incredible view, but I accepted. In glorious fashion, the Leafs
proceeded to play their worst game of the season. Of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there was a lot of empirical evidence that suggested the Leafs
were due for a bad game, when we returned to the parking lot, I figured
out the exact reason that the Leafs lost. In my excitement to get into
the arena, I stupidly parked in spot #67, which, of course, is the
number that fans of opposing teams derisively yell at us to remind us of
the last year that we won a championship. Oh, and on top of that, the
battery in the car was dead and we had to wait 90 minutes for roadside
assistance to unlock the Zipcar and charge the battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks, Leafs. See you in April.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//2014/02/05/the-maple-leafs-forever-unfortunately/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//2014/02/05/the-maple-leafs-forever-unfortunately/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A new outlook on social media</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is going to be hard. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been a loyal Facebook user since 2005, I’ve decided to part ways with, or at least ignore, what has become one of my strongest and most consistent connections to my extended group of friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I cherish the countless inspiring, hilarious, and otherwise absurd interactions I’ve had on Facebook over the years, it has come to a point where it seems that I can no longer regulate my own participation in an ever-widening social web that seems to be spiraling out of control. Posts disappear, random strangers show up, and privacy settings seem to change daily. Buzzfeed, Upworthy, and other horrible memes abound. It is a constant time-suck.\&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blogger and Twitter provide a more straightforward stream of information with which I can interact more easily. Both are wonderfully simple platforms. I can post. I can delete posts. I can edit posts! I am in control of what it looks like, and in what order it’s presented. It’s all public, and open. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last consistently updated blog existed before I had a Facebook account. Hopefully, this is a good time to start again.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//2014/02/04/a-new-outlook-on-social-media/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//2014/02/04/a-new-outlook-on-social-media/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Another kick at the can</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, and welcome to yet another rendition of a blog brought to you by Bryn Hughes. I’m already cringing at the predictible opening apology that begins this and so many other restarted blogs (“No, really, this time, FOR SURE!”). I’ve tried this several times over the years; some times more successful than others; and hopefully this time it will stick. As Count Basie used to say, “let’s hear it one more, once!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that I’m a musician and a music theorist, you can expect that lots of the content here will be of the nerdy/scholarly variety. In addition, I may delve into discussions about some of my other interests, including hockey, the Toronto Maple Leafs, flipped pedagogy, open-source scholarship (including GitHub, through whom this site is hosted!), and the joy and terror surrounding my impending fatherhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned! (Do kids even know exactly what that means anymore?)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>//2013/06/01/another-kick-at-the-can/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//2013/06/01/another-kick-at-the-can/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
